Guide to the Lawrence I. Grinnell papers, 1930-1977
Grinnell, Lawrence I. papers, 1930-1977
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Lawrence I. Grinnell papers, 1930-1977
2649
Lawrence I. (Lawrence Irving) Grinnell, 1889-1985.
7.3 cubic ft.
Field journals; reports; lecture notes; data; films, photographs, and photograph albums; correspondence; financial records; maps; printed materials; bird guides; and audiotapes.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
More than 70 motion picture films, photographic and written materials regarding ornithological trips taken by Lawrence Grinnell from 1938 to 1971; correspondence and a pamphlet, "The 1957-1958 New Zealand-Australia Expedition of the Laboratory of Ornithology"; materials pertaining to his dissertation A Study of the Common Redpoll, a notebook of Cornell ornithology seminars and Canoeable Waterways of New York State and Vicinity written by Grinnell.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Lawrence I. Grinnell was an ornithologist. He earned an M.S. in 1943 and a Ph.D. in 1947, both from Cornell University.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Field journals; reports; lecture notes; data; films, photographs, an audiotape, and photograph albums; correspondence; financial records; maps; printed materials; and bird guides regarding ornithological trips taken by Lawrence Grinnell from 1938 to 1971: St. Lawrence Gulf, Churchill (Manitoba), Alaska, Southern and Western United States, Trinidad, Guatemala, Colombia, Mexico, West Indies, Tobago, British Guiana, Panama, Africa, New Zealand, Australia, the Amazon region, Brazil, Venezuela, Peru, the Antarctic, India, and Nepal; also, correspondence and a pamphlet, "The 1957-1958 New Zealand-Australia Expedition of the Laboratory of Ornithology"; materials pertaining to his dissertation A Study of the Common Redpoll a notebook of Cornell ornithology seminars and Canoeable Waterways of New York State and Vicinity.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Grinnell, Lawrence I. (Lawrence Irving), 1889-1985.; Grinnell, Lawrence I. (Lawrence Irving), 1889-1985. New Zealand-Australia expedition of the Laboratory of Ornithology, 1957-1958.; Grinnell, Lawrence I. (Lawrence Irving), 1889-1985. Study of the common redpoll.; Grinnell, Lawrence I. (Lawrence Irving),1889-1895. Canoeable Waterways of New York State and Vicinity.; Cornell University--Faculty.; Cornell University. Laboratory of Ornithology.
Subjects:
Ornithology.; Ornithologists.; Scientific expeditions--Guatemala.; Scientific expeditions--Colombia.; Scientific expeditions--Mexico.; Scientific expeditions--West Indies.; Scientific expeditions--Guiana.; Scientific expeditions--Panama.; Scientific expeditions--Africa.; Scientific expeditions--Saint Lawrence, Gulf of.; Scientific expeditions--Manitoba--Churchill.; Scientific expeditions--Alaska.; Scientific expeditions--Trinidad.; Scientific expeditions--Tobago.; Scientific expeditions--New Zealand.; Scientific expeditions--Australia.; Scientific expeditions--Brazil.; Scientific expeditions--Peru.; Scientific expeditions--Venezuela.; Scientific expeditions--India.; Scientific expeditions--Nepal.; Scientific expeditions--Antarctic regions.; Scientific expeditions--Amazon River Region.; Scientific expeditions--United States.
Form and Genre Terms:
Field notes.; Photographs.; Slides (photographs).; Motion pictures (visual works).
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIAL
Lawrence I. Grinnell, "A Century of Unitarian History in Ithaca, 1865-1965." Pamphlet, #1525.
Correspondence and other material related to Lawrence Grinnell appears in the Arthur Augustus Allen papers, #21-18-1255 with whom he worked at the Laboratory of Ornithology.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Field Journals of Ornithological Trips
Box 1 & 3
Series II. Expedition Materials, Lecture and Film Notes
Boxes 2 & 4
Series III. Research, Manuscripts and Printed Materials by and about Grinnell
Boxes 2 & 4
Series IV. Photographic Materials
Box 3, 5, & 7
Albums
Prints
35mm Slides
Series V. Motion Picture Films
Boxes 5-8
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Field Journals of Ornithological Trips
  - Southwestern Trip and Misc. Articles, 1930 (Box 3)
  - St. Lawrence Gulf (books I-II), 1939 (Box 1)
  - Churchville, Man., 1940 (Box 1)
  - Alaska, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Southern and Western U.S., 1942 (Box 1)
  - Trinidad, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Guatemala, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Colombia, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Mexico--Yucatan, 1949 (Box 1)
  - West Indies, 1950 (Box 1)
  - West Indies, British Guiana, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Tobago, British Guiana, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Panama, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Africa, 1955 (Box 1)
  - New Zealand, Australia, 1957-1958 (Box 1)
  - Ohio R and Pine Creek, 1957-1958 (Box 3)
  - Salmon River, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Australia, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Current River Trip, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Africa, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Florida, 1961 (Box 3)
  - Europe, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Mexico, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Brazil, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Amazon, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Africa, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Venezuela (2 copies), 1965 (Box 1)
  - Venezuela, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Guatemala, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Nepal, India, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Brazil safari, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Galapagos, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Madagascar, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Atlantic Subantarctic Islands, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Indian Ocean, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Antarctic-New Guinea, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Antarctic-New Guinea, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Bird journal, undated (Box 1)
  - Bird statistics, undated (Box 1)
  - Field cards, undated (Box 1)
- Series II. Expedition Materials, Lecture and Film Notes
  - Florida birds, 1938-1952 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Alaska--birds and flora, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Alaska Talk, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Southern Trip: Bird and Flora Lists, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Trinidad, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Tropical Birds of Trinidad and Tobago Talk, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Includes notes for film
  - Trinidad Article, c. 1946 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Birds of Guatemala--lecture notes, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Guatemala, 1947, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Colombia, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Birds of Colombia - Lecture Notes, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Mexico--Yucatan, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Mexico-Yucatan Trip, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    American Ornithological Union Talk. Corresponding notes for film
  - West Indies, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - British Guiana, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - British Guiana, 1951-1952, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Panama, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Panama Trip - Lecture Notes, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Florida Trip: Notebooks, 1955 and 1957 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Florida Trip, 1955 and 1957 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Includes notes for Film
  - Africa, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - African Trip, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - New Zealand Trip - Lecture Notes, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - New Zealand-Australia Slide List and Map, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - New Zealand-Australia, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Includes notes on sound for film
  - Australian Trips, 1957-1959 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    General notes, lecture notes and notes for film.
  - The 1957-1958 New Zealand-Australia Expedition of the Laboratory of Ornithology (printed report) (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - New Zealand-Australia, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - New Zealand-Australia, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - New Zealand-Australia, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - New Zealand-Australia, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Australia--bird guides, 1957, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Australia--data, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Australia Sound Script, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Southwestern US, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Notes for film
  - Africa, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Wildlife of East Africa, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    General notes and notes for film
  - European Bird Tour, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Lecture notes and notes for film
  - Map of Brazil, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Brazil, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    General notes, lecture notes and notes for film
  - Brazil--report, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Brazil, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Brazil--correspondence, etc., 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Venezuela, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Venezuela, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Venezuela, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - British Guiana, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - India, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Peru, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Peru--printed materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Amazon safari, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Antarctic, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Antarctic, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Antarctic, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Antarctic, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Birds of Madagascar--lecture notes, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Madagascar, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Indian Ocean Islands, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Indian Ocean--lecture notes, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - South Atlantic--lecture notes, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Atlantic Subantarctic Islands, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Antarctica--McMurdo, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - New Guinea, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - New Guinea, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - New Guinea (Lecture Notes), 1971 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Birds of Eastern US (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - List of Motion Picture Photography Tours, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
    List of films made during expedition trips from 1938-1971
- Series III. Research, Manuscripts and Printed Materials by and about Grinnell
  - Article on St Lawrence Gulf, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Churchill--common redpoll supporting data, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Churchill--original negatives, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Churchill--summer redpoll records and other, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Churchill, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Notes on Breeding Lapland Longspurs at Churchill Manitoba, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Life History of the Common Redpoll, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Articles by Grinnell, 1941 and 1943 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    "Notes on Bird-Life of Churchill, Manitoba" and "Nesting Habits of the Common Redpoll"
  - Thesis: A Study of the Common Redpoll, p. 1-40, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Thesis: A Study of the Common Redpoll, p. 41-113, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Thesis: A Study of the Common Redpoll, p. 114-173, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Thesis: A Study of the Common Redpoll, p. 174-225, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Notes (Box 4, Folder 35)
    Irregular winter bird visitors, Salomonssen: Evolution of Redpolls and Lapland Longspurs
  - A Century of Unitarian History in Ithaca by Lawrence Grinnell, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Article About Lawrence I. Grinnell, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Passarine birds of the world, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - "Canoeable Rivers in Central New York State", 1952 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Canoeing Lectures, c. 1972 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Canoeable Waterways of New York State, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    Photocopy of the title page with an inscription by Grinnell.
  - Canoeable Waterways of New York State, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Canoe Trips of New York State no. 1, undated (Box 4)
  - Canoe Trips no. 1, undated (Box 4)
  - Canoe Trips no. 2, undated (Box 4)
  - Remarks on the Distribution of the Corpuelis Limaria: Translated from German, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Seminars in Ornithology: C.U. Lab of Ornithology (I-IV), undated (Box 3)
- Series IV. Photographic Materials
  - Albums
    - India, Nepal, 1967 (Box 3)
    - New Zealand--bird photos--K.V. Bigwood, undated (Box 3)
    - Australia, 1959 (Box 3)
    - Africa, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Color photos of birds and flora, undated (Box 3)
  - Prints
    - Prints from Churchill, Manitoba (not birds), 1940 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Photographs for article on Common Redpoll, c. 1940 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Canoeable Waterways of New York - matted photograph and cover, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Photograph is number 35
    - Canoeable Waterways of New York - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 35mm Slides
    - Research for Common Redbill, Churchill, Manitoba, 1940 (Box 5)
      Used for Cornell Ph.D. Thesis
    - Churchill Slides, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Alaska: Plants, Sheets 1-4, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Alaska: Plants, Sheets 5-8, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Alaska - Plants, 1941-1942 (Box 7)
    - Ithaca, Trinidad, Guatemala, Colombia: Birds, 1946-1948 (Box 7)
    - Columbia and New Zealand, c. 1948 (Box 5)
    - East Australia and Southwest US, 1959-1960 (Box 7)
    - Venezule, British Guiana, Guatemala, India, Nepal, 1965-1967 (Box 7)
    - Venezuela, British Guiana, Guatemala, India and Nepal, 1965-1969 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Africa, Amazon, Brazil, Venezuela, undated (Box 7)
    - Cornell Laboratory of Ornithology, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Series V. Motion Picture Films
  - Zermatt Gorge Matterhorn, 1930; F-749 (Box 6)
    1 3.75in reel: b&w; 16mm
  - Birds of St Lawrence Gulf: Reels 1 and 2, 1939; F-750 & F-751 (Box 6)
    2 7in reels: b&w; 16mm
  - Birds of the Hudson Bay Tundra: Reels 1 and 2, 1940; F-752 & F-753 (Box 6)
    2 7in reels: col.; 16mm
  - Alaska: Reels 1 and 2, 1941; F-784 & F-785 (Box 7)
  - Trinidad: Reels 1-3, 1946; F-754 - F-756 (Box 6)
    3 7in reels: col.; 16mm
  - Guatemala: Reels 1 and 2, 1947; F-757 & F-758 (Box 6)
  - Colombia: Reels 1-3, 1948; F-759 - F-761 (Box 6)
  - Mexico-Yucatan: Reels 1-3, 1949; F-762 - F-764 (Box 7)
  - Esopus Creek, Jamaica and St. Lawrence, 1951; F-773 (Box 6)
    1 7in reel: col.; 16mm
  - British Guiana: Original Reels 2-4, 1951-1952; F-726 - F-728 (Box 5)
  - British Guiana: Duplicate Reels 1 and 2, 1951-1952; F-729 & F-730 (Box 5)
  - Birds and Gardens from West Indies to British Guiana: Reels 1-5, 1951-1952; F-731 - F-735 (Box 5)
    5 7in reels: col.; 16mm
  - Panama: Reels 1-3, 1954; F-736 - F-738 (Box 5)
  - Florida, 1955; F-765 (Box 7)
  - Africa: Reels 1-4, 1955; F-766 - F-769 (Box 6)
    4 7in reels: col.; 16mm
  - New Zealand, 1957; F-739 (Box 5)
    1 7in reel: sd., col.; 16mm
  - Australia - Bulbul, 1957; F-770 (Box 6)
    1 3.75in reel: col.; 16mm
  - Australia (Extras): Reels 1 and 2, 1957 and 1959; F-771 & F-772 (Box 6)
  - Australia: Sound Tape Reel, 1957; TR-9882 (Box 6)
  - Island of Hawaii, 1958; F-774 (Box 6)
  - Salmon River, August 1958; F-786 (Box 7)
  - Fiji, 1959; F-740 (Box 5)
  - South Atlantic Islands, 1959; F-800 (Box 6)
    1 12.5in reel: col.; 16mm
  - Australia, 1959; F-789 (Box 7)
  - Southwestern United States: Reels 1 and 2, 1960; F-775 & F-776 (Box 6)
  - Africa: Reels 1 and 2, 1961; F-790 & F-791 (Box 8)
    2 12.5in reels: col.; 16mm
  - Birds of Monte, c.1961; F-741 (Box 5)
  - Europe (Sweden), 1962; F-777 (Box 6)
  - Iceland-Europe, 1962; F-792 (Box 8)
    1 10.75in reel: col.; 16mm
  - Vislumbre Sud Mexicano, 1963; F-778 (Box 6)
  - Brazil: Reels 1 and 2, 1963-1964; F-793 & F-794 (Box 8)
  - Lab Birds, 1965; F-745 (Box 5)
  - Hobart?, 1965; F-747 (Box 5)
  - Venezuela: Reels 1 and 2, 1965; F-795 & F-796 (Box 8)
    2 10.75in reels: col.; 16mm
  - Canoeing, 1966; F-787 (Box 7)
  - British Guiana, 1966; F-742 (Box 5)
  - Amazon Safari, 1968; F-743 (Box 5)
  - Galapagos Islands, 1968; F-797 (Box 8)
  - Antarctica, 1968-1969; F-799 (Box 8)
  - Mt. Kilimanjaro Madagascar, 1969; F-779 (Box 6)
  - Patagonia, 1969; F-780 (Box 6)
  - Indian Ocean Islands, 1970; F-744 (Box 5)
  - New Guinea, 1971; F-798 (Box 8)
  - Panama: End of Reel 1?, undated; F-746 (Box 5)
  - Untitled Film, undated; F-748 (Box 5)
  - Birds of Eastern United States: Reel #2, undated; F-781 (Box 6)
  - Tree-tops, undated; F-782 (Box 6)
  - Mountain Climbing, undated; F-783 (Box 6)
    1 7in reel: b&w; 16mm
  - Canoeing #4 Dinosaur, undated; F-788 (Box 7)